

Europass curriculum vitae

TISCHER Daniel

C/ Nueva 18, E-03430, ONIL (Alicante), SPAIN +34 627 016 140

daniel.tischer@yahoo.es

Nationalities
Date of birth
Gender

German & French 06/05/1972 (age 40) Male

Desired employment / Occupational field

DevOps Engineer

Summary

I have a java developer background and like participating hands-on in every project I do. In the last 15 years, I also had several experiences in business analysis and project management with close contact to operations. Mostly working for European Institutions, I was involved in challenging long-term projects, my last contract allowing me to setup a new software organization from ground up.

Work experience

Dates

February 2008 - Today

Occupation or position held

Software Architect and Technical Lead

Main activities and responsibilities

Responsible for the application of software quality standards, I supported 3rd party suppliers with technical orientation and a reference framework. Later, I introduced Continuous Integration and Delivery and refactored the documentation: unified templates, versioning, single sourcing, and automatic class-diagram generation in the Javadocs (comments in the coded instructions).

As part of the Simplification Programme, I lead the Software Industrialization project, a continuation to the proof of concept and reference application created by myself. This application resolves many standard problems that developers face when starting a new project.

Technologies

Java 1.7, Spring 3.1, Hibernate 4, JPA 2, AspectJ, Lucene/SOLR, JMock, Junit, DBUnit, Cactus, Selenium, JMeter, Checkstyle, Findbugs, PMD, Apache, Ant, Maven, Javadoc, Doxygen, Doxia, GraphViz, GIT, Subversion (SVN), REST, XML/XSL, HTML, CSS, Eclipse, Oracle, Informix, MySQL, HSQL, H2, Derby, Apache Tomcat, WebLogic, JBoss, Sonatype Nexus, Jenkins, Sonar, TestLink, Atlassian Jira, Fisheye, Crucible, Crowd, Cloudbees, VMware, MediaWiki, PDF generation (mwlib).

Name and address of employer

OHIM Office for Harmonization in the Internal Market, Alicante, Spain (Temporary Agent).

Dates

June 2006 - December 2007

Occupation or position held

Business Analyst

Main activities and responsibilities

Fee Management – OHIM / Quality Management Department (QMD) & Finance Department

Optimized fee management processes across 3 organisational units. This includes organisational and technical measures to automate manual tasks and make the processes more cost-efficient.

I organised and moderated meetings with key users, gathered new requirements and came up with sensible and innovative recommendations. I applied my experience in architectural design to avoid data duplication and harmonise interfaces with other application modules, not forgetting qualitative aspects (response time and data integrity for payments).

Name and address of employer

OHIM Office for Harmonization in the Internal Market, Alicante, Spain, infeurope S.A. for the Office.

Dates

October 2004 - May 2006

Page 1 - Curriculum vitae of

For more information go to http://europass.cedefop.europa.eu

TISCHER Daniel

© European Communities, 2003

Last update: 26/02/2013

Occupation or position held

Senior Developer

Main activities and responsibilities

RECordals (EuroDesign-System) - OHIM / ITFMD

I coordinated the full development lifecycle between Luxembourg and Alicante, from requirements gathering to prototyping and development to test. I was the first to introduce fully automated web tests at OHIM, and so dramatically reduced the testing period from one week to half a day. This allowed the team to work in shorter iterations and quickly adapt to changes.

To improve communication, I moderated the developer forum, set up a wiki (collaborative web site). In the end, I provided user training and knowledge transfer to those who had to take over.

Technologies

Java 1.4, Spring, Hibernate 3, JSP, JSF, Junit, JTestCase, Canoo WebTest, Clover, Cactus, Maven, Subversion (SVN), REST, XML/XSL, XSLT, XHTML, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Eclipse, Informix 7.1.3, WebLogic 8.1, Atlassian Jira, PowerDesigner, Rational Unified Process (RUP), UML.

Name and address of employer

OHIM Office for Harmonization in the Internal Market, Alicante, Spain, infeurope S.A. for the Office.

Dates

June 2003 - September 2004

Occupation or position held

Business Analyst

Main activities and responsibilities

Definition of Best Practices guidelines using methodologies such as RUP (Rational Unified Process), XP (Extreme Programming) and UML (Unified Modeling Language).

Project support for the OHIM EuroMarc++ CTM-EXAmination module to integrate it with over 30 modules in production. Consolidated requirements and use case reviews (UML) in a detailed Work Breakdown Structure (WBS) in order to clarify the needs and realize the planning for development.

Java, WebLogic and UML certification.

Technologies

Java, Subversion (SVN), EJB, WebLogic 6.1, Informix 7.1.3, FileNet P8 Process Engine 3.5, UML.

Name and address of employer

infeurope S.A. - 62, rue Charles Martel L-2134 Luxembourg

Dates

October 2001 - May 2003

Senior Developer

Occupation or position held

CPS - Common Payment System - OHIM / ITFMD

Main activities and responsibilities

Testing and setting in production of a Common Payment System (CPS), as a part of EuroDesign, a new development of 18 modules based on J2EE standards in a multi-tier architecture.

Analysis and development for OHIM in Luxembourg that involved optimising access to critical data between SAP, Informix and Oracle databases. Responsible for the communication interfaces with SAP (import/export) and accounting reports.

Technologies

Java 1.4, CVS, Turbine framework / Eclipse, JBuilder, EJB, Apache Tomcat 4.0, WebLogic 6.1, Oracle 8, Informix 7.1.3, Power Designer, Rational Team Test, Unified Process (RUP), UML.

Name and address of employer

OHIM Office for Harmonization in the Internal Market, Alicante, Spain, infeurope S.A. for the Office.

Dates

May 2000 - September 2001

Occupation or position held

Senior Developer

Main activities and responsibilities

SHAB - Swiss Official Gazette of Commerce (SOGC - SHAB - SECO), www.shab.ch

The SHAB is the only official publication of the Swiss Confederation, which is published five times a week and contains the most recent official information and legally prescribed announcements.

Functional requirements gathering and data modelling for XML entity persistence in a database.

Technologies

Java 1.2, XML, XSLT, JBuilder, Apache 1.3.12, Apache Tomcat, Oracle 8.1.6, Power Designer.

Name and address of employer

infeurope S.A. - 62, rue Charles Martel L-2134 Luxembourg

Page 2 - Curriculum vitae of

For more information go to http://europass.cedefop.europa.eu

TISCHER Daniel

© European Communities, 2003

Last update: 26/02/2013

Dates

January 2000 - April 2000

Occupation or position held

Project Manager

Main activities and responsibilities

TED Alert – Technical analysis, functional requirements analysis and modelling for the TED Alert Portal (Tenders Electronically Daily).

The TED Alert Service is a management information system based on automatic selection and distribution of public procurement.

Outlined architecture to index high volumes (80 GB / year) and integrate with Intershop Enfinity to provide additional (paying) services such as translation and advertising.

Technologies

Intershop Enfinity, Oracle 8, Photoshop, Dreamweaver

Name and address of employer

infeurope S.A. - 62, rue Charles Martel L-2134 Luxembourg

Dates

March 1998 - December 1999

Occupation or position held

Developer

Main activities and responsibilities

SIMAP – Design and implementation of the Système d'Information pour les Marchés Publics (SIMAP) under the direction of the European Commission, <u>simap.europa.eu</u>

This Java web development replaced two pilot projects: a personal computer based software with a graphical user interface to control data entry of standard public procurement forms, and a search and retrieval tool to disseminate the procurement information.

Technologies

Java 1.2, Applets and Servlets, JDBC, SQLJ, Perl 5, JavaScript, Ajax (DHTML), PHP 3, XML, Omnimark, Netscape Suitespot, JRun, WAI CoolRunner (Servlet Engine), 8, MS-Access, MySQL.

Name and address of employer

infeurope S.A. - 62, rue Charles Martel L-2134 Luxembourg

Dates

August 1997 – February 1998

Occupation or position held

Systems Analyst

Main activities and responsibilities

Installation and administration of infeurope's computer network (more than 100 machines in mixed Windows and Unix environment) for which I provided 24/7 support service.

Administration of Luxembourg's Parliaments Internet Platform: Web servers, News servers, Mail servers (Sun Solaris).

Name and address of employer

infeurope S.A. - 62, rue Charles Martel L-2134 Luxembourg

Dates

November 1995 – July 1997

Occupation or position held

Translator, Developer, Trainer

Main activities and responsibilities

Translation and localization to the French Market of the international business and accountancy software Navision financials (includes a proprietary database). Training, development and support of the Navision Solution Centre Network.

Microsoft acquired Navision in 2002.

Name and address of employer

Navision Software France – 10, avenue Molière, 67200 Strasbourg, France

Education and training

Dates Days 2012 4		Principal subjects / occupational skills covered	Cert.	Organisation	
		516 - Best Practices in Java Programming: Hands-On		Learning Tree	
2012	5	446 - Preparing for the CompTIA Security+ Exam	Yes	Learning Tree	
2010	5	Oracle Service Bus 10g R3: Administration and Development		Oracle University	
2010	4	294 - Influence Skills: Getting Results Without Direct Authority		Learning Tree	
2009	2	Terracotta's JVM-level clustering technology		Skillsmatter	
2008	3	424 - Service-Oriented Architecture (SOA)		Learning Tree	
2008	40	Programme of the Cambridge Certificate in Advanced English (CAE)		Linguarama	
2007	2	ISTQB ® Certified Tester, Foundation	Yes	Bogdan BEREZA	
2007	5	Prince 2 Practitioner Certification	Yes	QRP Management	
2006	2	Fundamentals of BPM through the introduction of BPMN specification		Ken SHERRY	
2006	2	ITIL Service Manager's Foundation Certification	Yes	Exagon	
2005	5	Spring and Hibernate - J2EE Technology Workshop		Jürgen HÖLLER	
2005	7	Project Management Professional (PMP ®) Certification	Yes	IIL	
2005	-	Sun Certified Web Component Developer (SCWCD Exam CX-310-081)	Yes	Sun Microsystems	
2004	-	Sun Certified Programmer for the Java 2 Platform (SCJP Exam CX-310-035)	Yes	Sun Microsystems	
2004	-	OMG Certified UML Professional Fundamental (Exam OM0-100)	Yes	OMG	
2003	10	Bea WebLogic Server 8.1 Certified Specialist	Yes	BEA Systems, Inc.	
2002	3	NPS Infopark - Content Management Systems Specialist		Infopark AG	
1999	5	Oracle 8 - Database Administration		Sun Microsystems	
1998	5	JAVA for Programmers (SL-275)		Sun Microsystems	
1997	2	BMC PATROL - Configuration and Administration		ABIS Training	
1996	5	Microsoft Certified Professional (MCP) Windows NT Server 3.51	Yes	Expertease	
1995	5	Navision Financials - Business and Accountancy Software		Navision	

Dates

1993 – 1994

Name and type of organisation

Title of qualification awarded

Institut Universitaire de Technologie (I.U.T.) in Strasbourg, <u>www-iut-schuman.u-strasbg.fr</u>

Diploma of Marketing Techniques (DUT)

Dates

1991 - 1993

Name and type of organisation

Title of qualification awarded

Institut Universitaire de Technologie (I.U.T.) in Strasbourg, www-iut-schuman.u-strasbg.fr

Diploma of Computer Science & Management (DUT)

Dates

1990 - 1991

Name and type of organisation

Universität des Saarlandes (Saarland University), Germany, www.uni-saarland.de

Title of qualification awarded

Accountancy Certificate

Page 4 - Curriculum vitae of TISCHER Daniel

For more information go to http://europass.cedefop.europa.eu

© European Communities, 2003

Last update: 26/02/2013

Dates (from - to)

1983 - 1990

Name and type of organisation

Ecole Internationale des Pontonniers, Strasbourg

Title of qualification awarded

General High school Certificate (Baccalauréat + Abitur), Scientific Section

Personal skills and competences

Languages European level

French

German

English

Spanish

Understanding				Speaking				Writing	
Listening		Reading		Interaction		Production		ĺ	
C2	Proficient	C2	Proficient	C2	Proficient	C2	Proficient	C2	Proficient
C2	Proficient	C2	Proficient	C2	Proficient	C2	Proficient	C2	Proficient
C2	Proficient	C2	Proficient	C2	Proficient	C2	Proficient	C2	Proficient
C1	Proficient	C1	Proficient	C1	Proficient	C1	Proficient	C1	Proficient

Organisational skills and competences

As a project manager and technical lead, I suggested significant improvements to the development process such as a better coordination of the source repository and quality control.

Organized several international Aikido seminars in Alicante.

Technical skills and competences

Certification for PMI, Prince2, ITIL and UML; good understanding of Merise and CASE tools.

Programming

Java, Spring, Hibernate, JPA, AspectJ, J2EE, Servlets & EJB, Lucene/SOLR, JMock, Junit, DBUnit, Cactus, Selenium, JMeter, Checkstyle, Findbugs, PMD, Apache, Ant, Maven, Subversion (SVN), GIT, SOAP, REST, XML/XSL, XSLT, XHTML, HTML, CSS, PHP, JSP, JavaScript, Ajax, Perl, C.

Software Products

VMware, Eclipse, Oracle, Informix, MySQL, HSQL, H2, Derby, MS-Access, Power Designer, Apache Tomcat, WebLogic, JBoss, Sonatype Nexus, Jenkins, Sonar, TestLink, Atlassian Jira, Fisheye, Crucible, Crowd, Cloudbees, MediaWiki, ZendServer.

Computer skills and competences

Linux, Microsoft Windows, Microsoft Office (Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Outlook, Visio, Project).

Artistic skills and competences

Webmaster of www.aikidoalicante.es (and other smaller projects).

Writer of an instruction manual for the COBOL programming language (1993 and 1994).

Classic Guitar.

Other skills and competences

Aikido teacher (black belt, 2nd dan), Alpine skiing.

Driving licence(s)

Full European driving license.

Additional information

References

infeurope SA: Jérôme SCHMUTZ (+34 965 13 9057)
OHIM - QMD: Andrea Di CARLO (+34 965 13 9458)
OHIM - APQ: Rainer TRETTER (+34 965 13 9221)

Annexes

Any further information provided on request.

Page 5 - Curriculum vitae of TISCHER Daniel

For more information go to http://europass.cedefop.europa.eu

© European Communities, 2003